<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuits undermining of parliaments and Protestants with their foolish phancy of a toleration, discovered, and censured. Written by William Castle, for the confirmation of wavering Protestants, and the reducing of seduced papists.</title>
            <author>Castell, William, d. 1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E124_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E124[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuits undermining of parliaments and Protestants with their foolish phancy of a toleration, discovered, and censured. Written by William Castle, for the confirmation of wavering Protestants, and the reducing of seduced papists.</title>
                  <author>Castell, William, d. 1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G. for Joseph Hunscot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob:24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IESVITS UNDERMINING OF PARLIAMENTS AND PROTESTANTS With their fooliſh phancy of A TOLERATION, Diſcovered, and Cenſured.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>WILLIAM CASTLE,</hi> for the confirmation of wavering Proteſtants, and the reducing of ſeduced Papiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Joſeph Hunſcot.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156161:2"/>
            <head>THE IESVITS UNDERMINING OF Parliaments and Proteſtants VVith their fooliſh phancy of a TOLERATION Diſcovered, and Cenſured.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemeth to wiſe men exceeding ſtrange, that <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> a worne Souldier, a man of very little Learning (when he was meerly neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by breaking of his legge to leave <hi>Mars</hi> and follow <hi>Mercury</hi>) ſhould in leſſe then ten yeeres become ſuch a grand proficient, as to procure from the See of <hi>Rome</hi> the laſt new order of Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its; whoſe number at firſt was but ſmall. But after ſome time, the Pope finding them to be wel verſt and moſt acute in all kind of literature, exceeding active in undertaking, and men no leſſe able then willing to ſupport the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, which (without their unexpected riſing like Locuſts out of the pit) had undoubtedly long ſince fallen without any hope of recovery, their number was from time to time enlarged, untill it became as now
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:156161:2"/>it is in all Kingdomes (where the Pope hath any thing to doe) unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and unſatisfied. But it ſeemeth yet much more ſtrange that Chriſtian Princes, to whom the Jeſuits incomparable treaſons, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, adulteries, perfidious and crafty ſtratagems are ſo well known, ſhould permit any of theſe Locuſts to remaine within their coaſts. Yea or that Jeſuits themſelves whoſe matchleſſe treaſons and treacheries, ſince the time of reformation, have been ſo often diſcovered, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with no leſſe then ſetting their quarters aſſunder, ſhould be ſo audaciouſly confident as to conceive ſuch extraordinary power or policy in themſelves as to be able to reduce theſe Kingdomes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the blind obedience, I ſhould ſay the miſerable ſlavery of Antichriſt. And yet they have often attempted that ſince the beginning of King <hi>Iames</hi> his raigne, and are not yet ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly out of hope to effect it; notwithſtanding the preſent cleere diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their damnable deſignes, and the ſtrong oppoſition which is daily made againſt them: But the infernall practiſes, and moſt irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious poſitions of theſe Jeſults, the weake and improbable meanes which their carnall wiſdome hath propoſed unto themſelves, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the generall deteſtation of them and their tenents in theſe Kingdomes, may ſomewhat though not altogether ſecure us that they ſhall never be able to effect their ſo long deſired toleration, which once obtained an utter extirpation of Proteſtants might ſoon follow after, for ſuch are their principles. There was indeed not many yeers ſince ſome grounds of their hopes: when inſtead of being cloſe hid in vaults, they boldly walked the ſtreets; when inſtead of being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, and having the Law executed upon them, they were prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be Confeſſors to great Court-Ladies, where they were very plentifully fed, and royally maintained; when being impriſoned, they were ſoon enlarged by a Secretary of State, one of their owne ſociety: when they had an Arrchbiſhop after their owne heart, (from whom holding intelligence with the Pope) they found greater favour with him then did the ſincere profeſſors of the Goſpell. But that ſtill they ſhould flatter themſelves with a hope of a toleration, plainely ſheweth them to be (what they are) moſt audaciouſly bould and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently reſtleſſe, which that it may more plainly appeare, I ſhall here briefly diſcover ſo many of their helliſh poſitions and practiſes as may juſtly render them as wel formidable as odious.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156161:3"/>
            <p>To begin then with their dangerous poſitions: Firſt, they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that Princes are ſo ſubordinate to the Pope as that he may as he ſhall ſee cauſe diſcharge their Subjects from their loyalty and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; yea and depoſe them, and confer their Kingdomes at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: nay further, that in caſe they will not come in and ſubmit to his Holineſſe (after admonition and excommuication) that their ſubjects may and ought to riſe up againſt them and deſtroy them; which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, how contrary it is to Scripture, the often repeated precepts, and practices of the Prophets and Apoſtles, yea and of Chriſt himſelf ſufficiently declare.</p>
            <p>Here the Jeſuits as is their uſual manner double extreamly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the men they have to doe withall, if it be with a Papiſt they dare juſtifie the premiſes in each particular, in that the power and liberty of the Catholique Church is boundleſſe, and in that they kill them not as Kings, but as favourers of hereticks; but if they have to do with a Proteſtant, who abhorreth the very thought of depoſing much more of killing of Kings, then they ſay that it is but a private opinion of ſome over zealous Catholiques, not the doctrine of the whole Church. Againe, they anſwer by the way of recrimination, that the late armes of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the preſent preparations of <hi>England</hi> for war prove them to hold the foreſaid tenents. As if there were no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between diſcharging ſubjects from their due obedience, and the ſetting a Kingdome in fit poſture of war, when forraigne inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and homebred conſpiracies (in the judgement of Parliament, the Grand-Councell of the Land) do threaten the preſent utter ruine both of King and Kingdome. As if it were the ſame to deprive the King, or lay violent hand on the Lords anoynted, as to deſire his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment may be regulated according to law; or in caſe of extreame neceſſity to endeavour the removing the wicked from the King, which is ſo far from being diſhonourable or prejudiciall to his Majeſty, as that in the end it will prove the moſt effectuall means for the more firme eſtabliſhing of his throne. A ſecond deteſtable poſition of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, is that of equivocation, which they ſtile a ſafe holy mentall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; but we more properly the art of lying: for confirmation of which their lying reſervation they produce the authority of the Counſell of <hi>Conſtance, Anno</hi> 1414. which tooke it ſelfe not bound to keep faith with heretickes, though the ſame were ſolemnly ſworne.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156161:3"/>Whence they infer, they are much leſſe bound to ſpeake the truth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though urged by oath. And they further confirm that by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> who gave liberty to <hi>Hildeſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> to breake faith with <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turke, and perſwaded him to it. I wonder they doe not remember what the fearefull event was of the liberty ſo given, and taken; was not <hi>Hildeſlaus</hi> after many great victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries obtained, and a peace concluded, the moſt advantageous that ever was, upon the breaking of his faith, not only beaten in the battell when he was far ſtronger then ever, But he loſt his honour, his army, his life, the Empire of <hi>Greece,</hi> and a great part of his own Kingdom, which could never be recovered?</p>
            <p>Why doe not theſe acute learned Jeſuites remember that the oath is made to the living God, not to the dying man? were they ſo well ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in holy writ, as they pretend, they ſhould find miſerie and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be the reward of Perjury, and infidelity. Did not <hi>Zedekiah</hi> for breaking faith with a Pagan ſee his children and ſervants ſlain before his eyes, after which his own eyes were torn out of his head? How were the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> miſerably afflicted in King <hi>Davids</hi> time, with 3 yeares fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſlaying of the <hi>Gibeonites?</hi> whoſe preſervation was ſworne 400 yeares before, by the congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though it were fraudulently obtained by the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> yet the Iſraelites having by oath confirmed it in the name of the Lord dared not break it: And though <hi>Saul</hi> were ſo bold as to violate the covenant ſo ſolemnly ſworn, yet juſt vengeance ceaſed upon his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whereof ſeven of them were delivered into the hands of the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bennites</hi> whom they hanged up before the Lord, and the famine cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And although they account us Proteſtants but Hereticks, and infidells yet they might likewiſe remember that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſware to many unbelieving Princes, <hi>Iſaac</hi> gave his faith, and obſerved it to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melcch, Jacob</hi> and his ſonnes, eſpecially <hi>Joſeph,</hi> were allied and lived with the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> And for their diſtinctions in promiſes, it wil breed in ſhort time ſuch confuſion in all the ſtates of <hi>Europe,</hi> as there will be nothing more pernitious &amp; lamentable; For if a ſerious promiſe, much more a ſolemn oath ſhall not be kept inviolable upon what agreement may any rely upon? There are few towns, caſtles, Cities, governments, that are not bound by oath. The Proteſtant by oath taketh aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Papiſts. The Papiſts of the Proteſtants. Kings from their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156161:4"/>Subjects. Subjects from their Kings, By oathes the lives and ſtates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all men are tryed, and the whole religious world governned. How can this Kingdome, or any other ſtand long, if equivocation prevail ſo far as that things covenanted and ſorwn need not to be obſerved? This once known there can be no end of warre, nor hope of peace, nor ſafety to treat of. Shall it be made but a bait for lying, treaſon, and cruelty, by which our Predeceſſours paſſed through the armes of their enemies, &amp; through the weapons of their moſt hatefull ſoes. The <hi>Romanes</hi> ignorant of the true God, in their ſwearing, and contracting alliances were wont to ſay, O <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſmite, and with lightning blaſt him, whoſoever he be that is here with an intent to deceive; what can be more horrible, then to cover falſhood with the name of the living God? We may not touch them ſaid the Princes of <hi>Iſraell</hi> meaning the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> becauſe we have ſworn to them in the name of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God. Now then that Jeſuits dare to take libertie to themſelves and diſpence with others to equivocate to the breach of faith given upon oath, we may ſafely conclude that they give the greateſt wound to Chiſtian ſociety as ever it received</p>
            <p>A third no leſſe perilous then arrogant poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Jeſuits is blind obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their concluſions and commands, be they never ſo differing, nay never ſo contrary to the law of God, of nature, of nations. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by vertue of their order are bound to obey their generall, though his command extend to the killing of a King. And whereas their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall is ever a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> be the Jeſuites Engliſh, Scottiſh, French, Dutch or of any other nation whatſoever, he muſt venter upon the perſon of his own naturall Prince, rather then the Catholick King might ſuffer, and ſo the Romiſh cauſe (which is upon the matter onely ſupported by him) might come in jeopardy. But it doth not hence follow, that the people ſhould herein follow their blinde guides who dare publiſh to the world that they under his Holineſſe can par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſlippes to Gods commandements, But can affoord no pardon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe who breake the commandements of the Church, which how farre it doth derogate from the Majeſtie and authority of God, and his holy word let not onely religious, but even rationall men judge. I will now inſtance in one more no leſſe dangerous then blaſphemous poſition of Jeſuites, upon which the three former, and many more are grounded, namely, that the Church is above the Scriptures and ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156161:4"/>judgeth of the Scriptures, as that ſhe may reproove or reject Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as ſhe ſhall think fit, that the Church and the head thereof, the Pope, is the rule of faith, better known and farre more certaine then are the Scriptures, by whom Scripture ought to be judged, and not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pope or Church by Scripture, whereas in truth the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth ſuch a cleare and perfect light as may ſufficiently guide our feet in the way of truth, and fully inſtruct us what we are to believe, and what we are to doe, what to affect and what to hope, which foure contains the whole dutie of a Chriſtian. To ſay no more, the Church became the Church, by receiving, believing, and ſo lowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from which when it ſhall in any ſort vary it is, no more the Church of God. And now to their dangerous poſitions, I ſhall adde ſo many of their bloudy, nefarious practiſes, as may in all reaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due thoſe, who moſt admire and are moſt addicted to them, to deteſt and abandon them. It is well known how often and how miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly Queene <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> eſcaped their many cloſe contrived plots a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt her perſon, and kingdome. And it is no leſſe known that in the beginning of King <hi>Iames</hi> his raigne, an impudent petition for a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trived by father <hi>Garnet</hi> &amp; other Jeſuits was preferred to his Majeſty, but adviſedly rejected upon the Archbiſhop <hi>Abbots</hi> grave counſel to the King. Upon the rejecting of which their audacious peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion growing deſperate, they enterpriſed by the advice of the ſaid <hi>Garnet,</hi> the gunpowder-treaſon, the moſt cruell and barbarous as ever was heard of, which had it taken, it had been accompanied with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er effuſion of bloud, then was the maſſacre in <hi>France,</hi> but herein much more deſtructive, when King, Prince, Nobles, Gentry, and the whole wiſdome of the land ſhould have received an irrecoverable blow, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blown up in a moment: ſo as the amaſed headleſſe people not able to reſiſt them, and their army, being at an inſtant in readineſſe, they muſt have yeelded to them both in matter of religion, and liberty, or have been miſerably ſlaughtered by them, A man might reaſonably have concluded that ſuch a matchleſſe treaſon, and bloudy deſigne upon King and kingdome ſhould have produced execution of law to the extirpation of them, and a diſſipation of their Jeſuiticall adherents. But ſuch was then their intereſt with forrain Princes ſubject to <hi>Rome,</hi> eſpecially with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and his pentioners here, ſome of our Nobility, Church-papiſts (whoſe entertainment came to no leſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156161:5"/>then 3000 l. or 4000 l. a yeere) as that after execution done upon ſome few of them, the father due proſecution of Law was ſtopped, yea ſo powerfull and prevalent were our Spaniſh penſioners, with King <hi>Iames</hi> (a very wiſe Prince) as they by many importunate ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations induced him to yeeld to ſomethings, and to deny other things, which have, or may prove exceeding prejudiciall to him, and his royall poſterity, to the peace, and tranquility of the Kingdome, and the proteſtant religion now eſtabliſhed. Firſt, his Majeſty was drawn on to conclude a peace with the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> the moſt diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to this Kingdom as ever was, were it but for one particular (which indeed was reſted in but upon the concluding of the Articles) and it was this, that no Engliſh be permitted to trade in the Weſt-Indies, and if any did venture ſo to doe, they ſhould be hanged and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured without mercy. Hence it followed, that the Engliſh who had reſolved with the Netherlands for the ſending of ten thouſand men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them into thoſe parts, were ſo deterred, as that our beſt friends the Netherlands were left to ſhift for themſelves; who thanks be to God have got a greater footing in <hi>Braſill,</hi> (not the tenth part of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> yet bigger then three <hi>Englands</hi>) then that the Spaniard will be ever able to remove them thence. And whilſt the Engliſh have for many yeeres ſate ſtill, and have not in the generall dared to adventure into thoſe parts, the Pilatage into thoſe ſpacious and goodly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys hath been by us well nigh loſt, and the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſo well inabled by a yeerely abundant comming in of his vaſt treaſure there, to make full and due payment to his Jeſuiticall penſioners here, as that ever ſince they have performed ſuch faithfull ſervice unto him as may ſhortly prove deſtructive to theſe Kingdoms, if not timely foreſeene, and prevented by the wiſdome and bleſſed accord of his Majeſty, and this his preſent Parliament. And leſt any thing ſhould be wanting to the Catholique King undertaking the Catholique cauſe, his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full penſioners perſwaded King <hi>James</hi> to arme the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> with 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. peeces of Ordnance, under colour of which licence, one Sir <hi>Iohn Ferne</hi> tranſported twice as many more. What others did here in is not ſo well known; but by wiſe men who have had knowledge of former times, it is conceived that if the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> were as well prepared with men and ſhipping, as he is with guns and amunition from us, he might beat us with our own weapons.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156161:5"/>
            <p>A third thing wherin King <hi>Iames</hi> was ſtrangley abuſed by the Spaniſh pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners the beſt friends to Jeſuits, was that by reaſon of their continuall cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his boundleſſe prerogative a point, which Princes generally are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much pleaſed to heare of, his Majeſtie (though otherwiſe very iudicious) was at laſt drawne to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>affect and undervalue Parliaments as intrenching too much upon his royall prerogative by how much they did more carefully endeavour to preſerve the laws enacted, in their full ſtrength and to enact other laws as might tend but to due regulating of regall power, which ought never to exceed law, but when it tendeth to the releife of the ſubject in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigating the vigour of law, not to the oppreſſing and impoveriſhing of them with illegall Monopolies, and unwarrantable taxations.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance in many other particulars, but one more ſhall ſuffice to ſhew how prevalent the Spaniſh faction were with King <hi>Iames,</hi> when upon the motion of <hi>Gundumore</hi> that arch politician ſeconded by their ſtrong approbation, his Majeſty neglecting the profers of ſome German Proteſtant Princes, did condeſcend to ſend his only ſonne and heire into <hi>Spaine</hi> for the contracting of a mariage there with the Spaniſh Kings Siſter, one of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Religion, which had it accordingly proceeded, it might have proved more inconvenient and troubleſome then hath his mariage with <hi>France.</hi> How the Jeſuits, and Jeſuiticall Spaniſh penſioners plots have ſucceeded ſince the acceſſe of his Majeſty that now is, unto the Crowne, I need not rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te at large, the wiſdome of this preſent Parliament hath ſaved mee that labor in their firſt unanſwerable remonſtrance. I ſhall therefore only breifly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome of the chiefe, after which I ſhall lay forth their yet more bold practizes, and bloody executions in <hi>France,</hi> and elſe where.</p>
            <p>The firſt was the laying of their foundation at the conclave at <hi>Rome</hi> wher it was concluded that his holines ſhould have a Nuntio in <hi>England,</hi> and the Queene of <hi>England</hi> ſhould have an agent at <hi>Rome</hi> to act things here, as ſhould be there reſolved upon.</p>
            <p>The 2. was to perſwade his Majeſtie by meditation of the Queene (whom they too well knew) he did as entirely love, as if ſhe had bin of his owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to preferr thoſe to places of dignitie at Court and of judicature both in Church, and common weale as might ſerve to put in execution their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewous deſignes. Whence it came moſt unhappily to paſſe that the Spaniſh penſioners became here Cabinet Councellors, ſo uſually over-awing, and overſwaying the farre greater, and better part of the privy Councell, as that their meere propoſalls paſt for reſolutions: and hence it was that the Star-chamber (where theſe Jeſuiticall penſioners and ſuch as they had promoted bare Sway) did abound with extravagate cenſures no leſſe unconſionable, then terrible, to the oppreſſing of the common people, by maintaining illegall taxations, and unwarrantable monopolies and in advancing prerogatives farr beyond all the preſidents of former times, And Shurely had it not bin for
<pb facs="tcp:156161:6"/>thoſe exceeding powerfull Popiſh factors, the high commition had no dareth ſo eagerly to oppoſe true Religion by ſuſpentions, deprivations, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, fines, and impriſonments much les would ſome Biſhops, and in eriour eccleſiaſticall Courts have adventured with ſuch animoſity: to propoſe or bitternes, to perſecute their owne ſuperſtitions articles: as if they had bin Cannons concluded upon by the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> (as then conſiſting only of Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, Cathedrall Prieſts and 2. ſuch country Clarkes as every Biſhop and his Sly officiall thought good off,) ought to bind the whole Church being ſo partially if not corruptly repreſented, For what are Cathedrall Church but ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and her Councell for ſome by Politicall ends were pleaſed to let reſt in ſome part of that Popiſt ſplendor which might take with neighboring Princes, and not render her, and her people utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly irreconcilable to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> when as yet the Parochill Churchs here were better clenſed from Popiſh relickes according to the well ſetled conſtitution of other reformed Churches, and yet for ſouth theſe better refined Parochiall Churches muſt againe be reduced to a Cathedrall garbe why. But that it is more ceremonecus, more Majeſticall and therin more reſembleth <hi>Rome.</hi> To conclude this point by reaſon of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweling greatneſſe of thoſe Cabinet Councellours, men were preferred to places of Judicature in the common-weale, which either could not, or would not maintaine Juſtice but were alwayes forward to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance prerogative, above and againſt law witneſſe ſome millions of mony in few yeares wreſted from the ſubject under the name of <hi>Loane Knighthood</hi> Shippe Coat, and conducte mony, by colour of forreſt law the Statute of improvement the commiſſion of ſevers abuſed Tunnage, and Poundage inhaunced by unwarrantable rates.</p>
            <p>All which though unlawfull yet were they all either juſtified by the moſt part of the Judges, or the people miſerablely oppreſſed (whilſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing debarred the uſuall remedy at law either by <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> or otherwiſe) they were left deſtitute of all legall defence for the preſervation of their goods, or perſons.</p>
            <p>A 3. Jeſuiticall plot was to weaken his Majeſty both at whom and ahroad. Which way could they more weaken him here in <hi>England</hi> then to employ the Cabinet Councell to peſwade him to make ſayle of his owne propper hereditary land, and to rayſe mony for the ſupporting of his royall Dignity, by unlawfull or unufuall meanes which could not but much with draw the dutifull affection of his ſubjects from him wherin his cheifeſt ſtrenght conſiſteth, And how could they have deviſed more to have leſſened the repute of his wiſdome and puiſſance with forraine Princes then by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing his Majeſty to begin warre and conclude peace both with <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156161:6"/>and <hi>Spaine,</hi> partly without and paetly againſt the approbation of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſwherunto may be added the takeing of <hi>Rochell</hi> by the aid of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſhips the little aſſiſtance, or countenance which of latrer times hath bin from <hi>England</hi> afforded unto our beſt friends the <hi>Neitherlands</hi> And from all theſe promiſes yet may ſtrongly be concluded that theſe were deſtructive wayes to the Proteſtant Religion and therefore promoted, and proſecuted by Jeſuits, and perſons Popiſtly addicted.</p>
            <p>A 4. plot as to overaw and impoweriſh the whole Kingdome by billiting ſouldiets in all parts of it, by intending to bring in forrain forces eſpecially many hundreds of <hi>German</hi> horſes and by propoſing Martiall law to be put in execution which had it taken affect, it would much more have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poweriſh the land then have many millions of mony exacted from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hince his Majeſties raigne; meerly under a pretence of law when there was neither reaſon, law nor equity for the raiſing of the leaſt part of thoſe infinite ſumme, which yet had they bin employed in any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proportion either for the good of King or Kingdome, neither King, nor Kingdome had bin ſo deſtreſſed as now they are. But the truth is as they were illegally impoſed, ſo they have bin as faudelently diſpoſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Majeſties privitie even to the ſtrenghtning of the profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion which now threatten no leſſe then the bringing under, if not the utter extirpation therof.</p>
            <p>A 5. deſigne was at once to imbrace, and imbecell the coyne of the Kingdome by making braſſe mony as currant, and more common then ſilver whilſt our gold was ſo ſlyly convoyed away as that in the greateſt pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the tenth of that gold, which formerly hath bin uſually mad, could in no place appeare, and how ſhould it be otherwiſe when the <hi>French</hi> (to omitt other nations) of all ſects and conditions from the higheſt to the loweſt, for the enriching of the Popiſh Jeſuiticall partie there have bin permitted to carry it away. How much Queene mother had for here ſhare is not exactly knowne but it is conceived upon very good grounds that ſhe, and her Jeſuiticall trayne have had 2 Millions of mony which is ten times as much as the Queene her daughter brought into this Land.</p>
            <p>Another deepe plot of the Jeſuits was grounded upon their intimate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, with <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>Wren</hi> and other ſuch like Popiſhly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted prelate whereby they procured the diſcountenancing yea and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the moſt able moſt ſincere and moſt faithfull Miniſters of the goſpell. When in the meane time countenance, and maintenance yea and the greateſt preferments were conferred upon <hi>Arminian Socinian</hi> Prieſts upon meert <hi>Formaliſts</hi> and time ſerving preachers whoſe poiſonous, tenents in ſomethings are the ſame with <hi>Rome,</hi> In other farre worſe and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as being more ſubtilly contriced.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156161:7"/>
            <p>Upon ſuch who had, onely a ſhew of godlineſſe &amp; were more for the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony then the ſubſtance of Religion: ſuch as were moſt forward in their Sermons at Court or in other eminent places to crie up the unlimited po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and prerogative of the King to the perverting of law and in as much as in them lay to the utter debarring of the people from their ancient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and immunities, from all right and property in their owne proper goods.</p>
            <p>But of all the Jeſuiticall plots that which is now in action: the ſeparating of his Majeſty from his Parliament and the working an ill opinion in ſome people and counties againſt their owne repreſentative body ſo adviſedly ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated in all ſhires, is moſt fearefull and admirably deſperate. For who could imagine (did it not evidently appeare) that the Jeſuits &amp; Spaniſh pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſhould have ſuch a powerfull influence with his Majeſty or be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Nobles &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non people as to make his Majeſty and them beleeve that this Parliament is ſet againſt him and the good of the land. And that Privados, Sycophantizing and time ſerving courtiers (who for the moſt part are blinded and tranſported with thoſe by reſpects of profit or preferment) ſhould be better affected, better able to ſee and adviſe then they are for the good and ſafetie both of King and Kingdome. This in the generall is the Jeſuits laſt plot now in agitation, but that conſiſteth of many branches very conſiderable: among which take ſpeciall notice of ſome few particulars here and there ſcattered in ſome papers lately publiſhed by the Jeſuiticall faction in his Majeſties name, whoſe perſon they have capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, and whoſe power they have ceazed upon. They dare boldly affirme with the greateſt confidence that the regall power is ſo derived from God, and the law as that it hath no dependance upon the truſt and conſent of man, but is abſolutely boundles and indefinitely ſupreame as well <hi>univerſis</hi> as <hi>ſingulis:</hi> ſo over all, that he may diſpoſe of all at pleaſure and be no way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to the Kingdome. That the being of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is meerely of grace, and may onely counſell in ſome things but not determine in any thing. That the major part in Parliament is not conſiderable when many are abſent or diſſent, or when ſome few overaw and over rule the reſt. That Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may doe diſhonorable nay treaſonable things and are queſtionable and triable elſewhere. As if it were probable that the wiſedome, &amp; till now the never ſuſpected integrity of both houſes of Parliament could ever prove ſo treacherous to King or Kingdome or ſo careleſſe of themſelves, and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity as to doe things diſhoneſt and treaſonable.</p>
            <p>Or as if it were credible that men for the moſt part never formerly knowne to his Majeſty, nor never greatly intruſted by him, or the State, ſhould be able to give more faithfull counſell then the Parliament, or to be leſſe ſubject to erroneous adviſes, to deſperate, and treaſonable reſolutions, then are thoſe who now ſit in Parliament, whoſe great paines, prudence, and
<pb facs="tcp:156161:7"/>patience, we to whom the benefit hath and will redound, have great cauſe to bleſſe God for; As if a few factious perſons (were they deſervedly ſo cenſured) were able to lead the whole Parliament the wiſedome of the land. That a country jury of twely men may be miſled by two ſubtile Knaves, is not muſuall, but that foure hundred or five hundred gentlemen, ſo conſiderately choſen as theſe were in all counties, ſhould be ſo abuſed, as without any ſhow of probability, Vnleſſe we conceive that thoſe few accuſed members worke by no ordinary meanes; And if it were granted (as few truly religious will grant it) that thoſe accuſed members were any way guilty of miſdemeanors, yea or of treaſon againſt his Majeſtie, and the government eſtabliſhed, yet it is but reaſonable that their offences ſhould be examined and decided by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: otherwiſe upon meere pretences the Parliament might be extrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſmembred, And in caſe the whole body of Parliament do erre, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reaſonably conceived, that the body of this Parliament, and their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions are queſtionable, and triable by any other power, then by ſome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Parliament.</p>
            <p>Oh then that all proteſtants, would ſeriouſly conſider how the foreſaid po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions tend to the diſſolving not only of this, but of all other Parliaments, without whoſe aſſiſtance neither our religion, nor our liberties have any hope of continuance, by reaſon of many helliſh ſubtile contrivements of Ieſuits, who as they have from their firſt originall diſturbed many other Nations, ſo now they have procured our preſent calamities, and a geeat effuſion of blood in Ireland I cannot at large relate what they have no leſſe tre cherou ly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived then bloodily executed in France, Germany, and other places, yet I may not altogether paſſe them over in regard we may be admoniſhed, and thereby armed againſt theſe firebrands of Chriſtendome, who in theſe our times are no leſſe inſolent, and dangerous to kingdomes, and States, then were their fore-fathers, and founders the Popes of Rome.</p>
            <p>The great Maſſacre of France, wherein were ſlain more then 50000, was the Ieſuits damnable plot, and ſo were the murders of the two French Kings Henry the third and Henry the fourth.</p>
            <p>Henry the third was bred a papiſt from his cradle, and when he became a man while he was Duke he was made generall of the popiſh forces, and gave the proteſtants that fatal blow at the battel of Mouncounter, and made them ſue for peace and after he was King, he maintained the Roman Religion to the uttermoſt of his power. And yet becauſe he gave peace to the Hugonets whom he could not conſtraine and becauſe he had compaſſion of his poore people eaten up with the armes of ſtrangers, And becauſe the cries of the widdow and fatherleſſe pierced his royall heart, and becauſe he would not deliver the crowne it ſelfe unto the hands of his vaſſals, he was wounded to death, and the fact approved as meritorious. And for Henry the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h though he changed the profeſſion of the proteſtant religion, which hee had
<pb facs="tcp:156161:8"/>profeſſed from his child-hood, and though he cauſed his owne children, and the next Princes of the blood to be trained up in popery, and to have Ieſuits for their Inſtructors, yet becauſe he would not continue the civil wair, in his owne country, and turne the ſword againſt the Huganites who had moſt faithfully ſerved him in his greateſt diſtreſſe, and becauſe he would not break of his leagues, and prove ungratefull to his proteſtant Princes and States which had aſſiſted him with men, and mony in attaining the crowne hee was ſhamefull, murdered by the procurement of Ieſuits. Oh that he had beene more conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the way of his religion, that he had depended more upon the power, and providence of the Almightie, and leſſe upon the arme of fleſh, for the preſervation and continuance of his kingdome, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that God who ſo often protected would alſo have protected him againſt Raveliack. And oh that our King would ſeriouſly conſider the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely end of both thoſe french Kings murdered by Ieſuits though profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and maintaining popery then might we hope that his Majeſtie who deepely profeſſeth to live, and die, in the proteſtant religion would cauſe the lawes to be ſeverely executed upon theſe King-killing Athiſticall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents for the Pope.</p>
            <p>In Germany the Duke of Saxony, and many more other Luthran Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, have of late been miſerably deluded by Ieſuits who induced them to ſtand Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ters whilſt the Emeprour with his Popiſh army plundered the moſt part of Germany, and hath perplexed, and well uigh deſtroyed that Goodly Country, with twenty yeares warre, Which hath conſumed many thouſands of Luthrans, as well as Calveniſts, al which ealamities, and ſlaughters might have beene prevented, had they not beene unhappily diſunited by the ſubtilety of Ieſuites. In Polonia now lately they have kindled ſuch a fire betwixt the King and his ſubjects, as that they who chooſe him with one generall conſent doe now thinke how to be ridd of him by reaſon that through their Councels hee entrencheth upon their Liberties more hee ought to doe.</p>
            <p>And in V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nis where Popery is profeſſed they have beene long ſince Banniſhed by reaſon of their treacheries, cruelties, and inſolent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te medling with ſtate affaires, wherein they doe but reſemble their holy Fathers the Popes of Rome whoſe pride, cruelties and treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were ſuch, as no Chriſtian could beleeve them, were they not recorded by their owne popiſh authors.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe Ieſuites the Poopes youngeſt ſonnes doe in all the forenamed reſpects and many more equal them eſpecially in regard of their audacious intermedling with State affaires.</p>
            <p>As the popes heretofore have diſturbed kingdomns, deſtroyed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and confirred kingdomes from nation to nation, from family to
<pb facs="tcp:156161:8"/>Family, ſo now his deare ſonnes the <hi>IES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITES</hi> take upon them, by his leave to doe no leſſe, How have they ſet the <hi>FRENCH</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>SPANNISH,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> The <hi>French</hi> againſt the <hi>Italians,</hi> The <hi>Italians</hi> againſt the <hi>French.</hi> The <hi>Spaniard</hi> againſt the <hi>Portugall,</hi> the <hi>Portuall,</hi> againſt the <hi>SPANIARD.</hi> But almoſt all Nations againſt <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> And the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hereunto annexed, as evidently appeareth by the great ſtore of ayde, ſhipping, men, money and all kinde of Warlike A nunition ſent, and to bee ſent, againſt theſe united Kingdomes from <hi>France, Spaine, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia, Denmarke. Dunkercke,</hi> and other Popiſh places of the Low Countries, whereof ſome have beene taken, others have unhappily eſcaped; but farre more are it in readineſſe and preparation to bee ſent.</p>
            <p>And ſhall wee permit ſuch Vipers as theſe <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and they Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuicticall Abetors are to live among us untill they have eaten up the bowells of the Common Weale, and which is it much more the life, and ſubſtance of true Religion by no by meanes: But let us ſtand and acquit our ſelves like men of Wiſedome, and courage, for the King and kingdome, but chefly for our GOD, and that pure Religion which for many yeares wee have now enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Let our wiſedome appeare firſt by our Piety, in crying mightily to God by ſeeking him by Faſting, Weeping and Mourning in truth and ſineerity and all other duties wherein wee may manifeſt our true humiliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. And then ſubmitting our owne particular underſtandings let us hearken unto and obſerve diligently the grave obſervations and directions and reſolutions of this preſent Parliament, which cannot chooſe but ſee more and decide better than any private man, yea or many men, be they never ſo wiſe, however men of no underſtanding, or men of no religion, or Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in religion, or of a contrary religion, either raſhly or malitiouſly dare to affirme the contrary.</p>
            <p>Let our courage appeare in a ſtout and reſolute oppoſition of all oppoſers of our Religion, and lawes eſtabliſhed more eſpecially againſt Ieſuits, and their abbettors who ſtrive fiercely even to the effuſion of much blood to diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbe and alter the Militia of the Kingdome, both by Sea and Land, under a fond pretence of defending the King and kingdome religion and law, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth they ſeeke the utter ſubverſion of them all. For how can it be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably imagined, that papiſts ſhould take up armes for the defence of the proteſtant religion, utlaws for the preſervation of the Law, or delinquents &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:156161:9"/>fugitives from parliament for priviledges of parliament which is the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative body of the kingdome And yet theſe are the men and but few o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of any better quality or condition who pretend to fight under the Kings Standard, againſt King and kingdome: A very ſtrong motive and unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable argument to incite all of any underſtanding or reſolution to ſtand firme to God and his truth for his Maieſty and royall poſterity, for the peace and ſafety of the realme againſt all forraigne invaſions and home-bred conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which neceſſary prudence and happy reſolution if it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to give unto the land in general, we need not much feare what either of them can doe againſt us. Our Militia by Sea ſo ſtrongly and ſo compleatly ſet forth and ſo well aſſiſted by our no leſſe gratefull then provident friends the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands may under God ſufficiently aſſure us againſt any great hurts from forraigne forces, though <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> though <hi>Denmarke</hi> &amp; <hi>Poland</hi> a thing very unlikely) ſhould at once joyne their forces of ſhipping men mony, horſe, and other warlike ammunition againſt us. And as for homebred conſpiracies, now that the wiſdome of the parliament hath ſo well contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and diſpoſed the order of the Militia in all countries ſo well approved of all (ſome few onely excepted as they intend by Gods aſſiſtance to live and die in the defence of it. The Ieſuits and their abbettors are very likely ere long to their ſhame and confuſion to finde their damnable plots to be fully diſcovered, their perſons and eſtates to be left to the ſeverity of law as is moſt juſt and but neceſſary for the preſervation of this Kingdome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
